Guide to the Frederick Stoever Dickson Collection Regarding William Makepeace Thackeray
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Frederick Stoever Dickson collection regarding William Makepeace Thackeray
1853-1912
1891-1912
GEN MSS 1100
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
12.42
(13 boxes)
The collection consists of manuscript and typescript material created by Frederick Stoever Dickson and others pertaining to Dickson's research on the life and work of William Makepeace Thackeray; included are letters to Dickson from authors, librarians, publishers, and other colleagues.
Dickson, Frederick Stoever, 1850-1925
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Frederick Stoever Dickson (Yale 1871), 1913; transferred from the Dickson Fielding Collection.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Frederick Stoever Dickson (1850-1925)
American lawyer, author, and collector.
Scope and Contents
The collection consists of manuscript and typescript material created by Frederick Stoever Dickson and others pertaining to Dickson's research on the life and work of William Makepeace Thackeray; included are letters to Dickson from authors, librarians, publishers, and other colleagues.
Arrangement
Organized into three series: I. Correspondence, 1891-1912. II. Writings, 1853-1911. III. Bibliographic Files, undated.
Authors, English -- 19th century; English literature -- 19th century; Card files -- United States -- 20th Century; Authors -- Great Britain -- 19th century; Dickson, Frederick Stoever, 1850-1925; Lambert, William H. (William Harrison), 1842-1912; Melville, Lewis, 1874-1932; Scudder, Horace Elisha, 1838-1902; Thackeray, William Makepeace, 1811-1863; Wilson, James Grant, 1832-1914; Houghton, Mifflin and Company
- Correspondence, 1891-1912; Series I; 8
  Scope and Contents
  Series I primarily contains letters to Dickson regarding his research on Thackeray's life and work.
  - Extracts from the letters of Edward Fitzgerald relating to William Makepeace Thackeray, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
    General note
    Manuscript copy in an unidentified hand [probably Dickson's]
  - Lambert, William H., 1894-1912 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Melville, Lewis and Helen, 1902-1912 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Scudder, Horace Elisha (Houghton, Mifflin and Company), 1891-1897 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Wilson, James Grant, 1901-1906 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - From various authors, 1892-1912 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - From booksellers, publishers, and others, 1891-1912 (Box 1, Folder 7-8)
- Writings, 1853-1911; Series II; 11
  Arrangement
  Series II is organized into three subseries: Writings by William Makepeace Thackeray, Writings by Frederick Stoever Dickson, and Writings by Others.
  The series contains printed versions and typescripts of writings by and about Thackeray.
  - Writings by William Makepeace Thackeray
    - "The Newcomes," chapter IV, clipping of printed version from Harper's New Monthly Magazine, no.43, 1853 Dec (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - "Thorns in the Cushion," Roundabout Papers, No. 5, clipping of printed version from The Cornhill Magazine, 1860 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - "On a Joke I once heard from the late Thomas Hood," Roundabout Papers, No. 9, clipping of printed version from The Cornhill Magazine, 1860 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - "On a Chalk-Mark on the Door," Roundabout Papers, No. 11, clipping of printed version from The Cornhill Magazine, 1861 Apr (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - "On Two Roundabout Papers which I intended to Write," Roundabout Papers, No. 16, clipping of printed version from The Cornhill Magazine, 1861 Sep (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - "Titmarsh's Tour through Turkeydom," typescript transcription from Frazer's Magazine (1846), undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Writings by Frederick Stoever Dickson
    - [Thackeray's Writings], typescript with autograph corrections, undated (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - "William Makepeace Thackeray," typescript with autograph corrections, undated (Box 1, Folder 16)
      For presentation to the Rowfant Club, Cleveland, Ohio.
    - Other material relating to Thackeray bibliography, undated (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Writings by Others
    - "Thackeray as a Reader and Critic of Books," by Lewis Melville, 1903 Nov (Box 1, Folder 18)
      Printed version, clipped from the Fortnightly Review.
    - "Rosebury on Thackeray," author unknown; newspaper clipping, 1911 Jul 18 (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Bibliographic Files, undated; Series III; 12; (12 boxes)
  The series holds boxes of Frederick Stoever Dickson's filing envelopes containing cards with bibliographic citations and notes. Miscellaneous small clippings (contemporary to Dickson) and unfiled bibliographic material are in boxes 12 and 13.
  - Authors, A-G, undated (Box 2)
  - Authors, G-M, undated (Box 3)
  - Authors, N-W, undated (Box 4)
  - Authors, W-Z, undated (Box 5)
  - Artists and photographers, A-Z, undated (Box 5)
  - Serials, A-Z, undated (Box 5)
  - Serials, A-E, undated (Box 6)
  - Serials, F-Q, undated (Box 7)
  - Serials, R-Z, undated (Box 8)
  - Letters, 1818-1863, undated (Box 8)
  - Ballads, A-G, undated (Box 8)
  - Ballads, H-Z, undated (Box 9)
  - Authors, A-Z, undated (Box 9)
  - Writings by Thackeray, A-C, undated (Box 9)
  - Writings by Thackeray, D-M, undated (Box 10)
  - Writings by Thackeray, N-Z, undated (Box 11)
  - Writings by Thackeray, works and miscellaneous, undated (Box 12)
  - Clippings, undated (Box 13)